Guide to the Colonial Africa: Postcard Collection, 1880-1980
Department of Special Collections
- Series 23. South Africa
  - Subseries 2. People and Wildlife
    - People and wildlifen.d., 19 postcards (Box 3, Folder 6)
      19 postcards from South Africa. Of these, 6 depict images of people, including a mother and her child, an old man; groups of people sitting outside of a hut; and a stone structure. The rest contain pictures of animals, including: Impala; Zebra; Giraffe; Kudu; Sable; Rhinoceros; Antelope; blue Wildebeest; Lion; Elephant; Bull Sealion; Penguins; Ostrich; Termite mound. These images are located at Kruger National Park; Drakensberg National Park, Natal; Mossel Bay, Cape Province; Dyer's Island, Cape Agulhas.
      Cl. J. Boyer; Perfinn; South African Railways and Harbours, Publicity and Travel Dept.; Children; Indigenous peoples; South Africa; Wildlife
- Series 24. Southeast Asia
  - Southeast Asian.d., 9 postcards (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Postcards from India, Indonesia, and Ceylon (Sri Lanka). Include: India: Anand, orphanage;Roberts Statue, Calcutta; Cawnpore; Mission des Carmes, Malabar; Indonesia: Kota Radja, Ceylon: catamaran; street scene; missionaries, Philippines: missionary school
    Grimaud, Marseille; Missions des Carmes au Malabar; Missions des Oblats de Marie Immaculee, Ceylon; Raphael Tuck & Sons; Boats, Ceylon (Sri Lanka); India; Missionaries; Monuments; Orphans; Philippines
- Series 25. Sudan, British
  - Sudan, Britishn.d., 23 postcards (Box 3, Folder 8)
    22 postcards of British Sudan, primarily Khartoum and Port Sudan. Images include the following: Khartoum: Palace and gardens; Gordon College; Parliament Building; Grand Hotel; Khedive Ave.; Blue Nile and Blue Nile Bridge; White Nile Bridge; Port Sudan: views of town; Mosque; Public garden; Wadi-Halfa: River view; street scene, Market, People: Battaheen Arabs; Man; Children
    Angelo H. Capato, Khartoum; D. P. Chryssides, Port Sudan; G.N. Morhig, English Pharmacy, Khartoum; Gordon Stationery, Khartoum; Lichtenstern & Harari, Cairo; M. Venieris, Khartoum; Sudan Railways; Sudan Times; Tropical Photo Stores, Karakashian Bris., Khartoum; Architecture, colonial; Bridges; Gardens; Indigenous peoples; Markets; Military facilities; Mosques; Rivers; Sudan
- Series 26. Togo
  - Togon.d., 3 postcards (Box 3, Folder 9)
    3 postcards from Togo. 2 similar with image of beach and oil rigs. One of Beach Anecho
    Edition A.-A. Acelaise; Librairie M.-A. Mayoux; Photo G. Menant; Beaches, Togo, Description and travel
- Series 27. Tunisia
  - Tunis n.d., 28 postcards (Box 3, Folder 10)
    These 28 postcards contain the following images of Tunis: Grande Mosque; marabout; artisanal boutiques; a cafe; prisoners wearing chains; Lycee Carnot; Cathedral; Palace of Justice; Post office, Marketplaces: Souk El Sekadjine (saddle-makers); Arab market; Arab coal market; Souk des Femmes; Souk El Attarine. Street scenes include: rue Sidi Ben Arous; rue des Etoffes; rue et Place Bab-Souika; rue Sidi ben Ziad; Ave. Jules Ferry; Le Square de la Residence; Place Anatole France, Avenue de Paris; Avenue Theodore Roustan; Rue du Pacha; Place des Selliers.
    CAP; Edit. Victor et Sauveur Brami, Tunis; EMT, LL Lehnert & Landrock, Cairo; ND Phot. Photo-ateliers Baudouin, Marseille; Architecture, colonial; Cafes; Markets; Mosques; Post offices; Prisoners; Religious buildings; Street scenes; Tunisia
  - Bizerte; Carthage; El Hamma; Kairouan; Korbous; Mahdia; Medinine; Sousse; Thuburbo-Majusn.d., 15 postcards (Box 3, Folder 11)
    15 postcards from various cities in Tunisia: Bizerte: Vieux Port, Carthage: Basilica of St. Cyprian, El Hamma: indigenous house, Kairouan: rue Saussier; doughnut sellers; marabout, Korbous: view; Mahdia: Post office, Medenine: street scene; Sousse: view; cathedral; Hotel Boujaffar; Thubarbo-Portique des Petronii; Indigenous tent (goubi); notary in his study
    CAP, EMT Editions Glatigny, Tunis; Editions Photo-Africaine, Alger; LL Levy et Neurdein Reunis, Paris; Musee de Lavigerie, Carthage; ND Phot.; Archaeological sites; Harbors; Hotels; Indigenous peoples; Markets; Panoramic views; Post offices; Religious buildings; Street scenes
- Series 28. Thematic
  - Subseries 1. Children
    - n.d., 30 postcards (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Postcards with images of children, mainly of North Africa and subsaharan Africa. Of note: some of the postcards seem to show erotic or homoerotic images. One postcard shows a young girl lying down with a sign in front of her wishing "Happy New Year, 1913"
      CAP; Cairo Postcard Trust, Cairo; Collection generale Fortier, Dakar; Collection L. Martin; Edition LY, Editions Hoa-Qui, Paris; Ern. Thill, Brussels; G.N. Morhig, Publisher, English Pharmacy, Khartoum; LL Lehnert & Landrock; Photo-Home, Leopoldville; Procure des Missions "Chine-Ceylan-Madagascar"; Societe des Missions Evangeliques, Paris; Africans; Arabs; Children
  - Subseries 2. Foods and Restaurants
    - Desert scenes, oases, oueds, caravansn.d., 50 postcards (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Postcards showing various views and activities in the Sahara Desert. Organized according to the following themes: dunes; caravans and camels; oeuds (springs in the desert); oasis; palm forests (palmeraies); seguias (desert rivers); marabouts
      A. Jouve, phot., Algiers; ADIA. Nice; Agenda P.L.M.; CAP Collection Ideale, P.S.; Edit. Aracil; Edit. Horizons de France; Edition Maurice Maure, Biskra; EMT Levy & Neurdein Reunis, Paris; LL ND Phot; Camels; Caravans; Deserts; Dunes; Indigenous peoples; Oases; Panoramic views
  - Subseries 3. Desert Scenes
    - Food and restaurantsn.d., 4 postcards (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Four postcards showing various "food scenes" in North Africa. Images include: Women making couscous; a "cafe maure"; a "cafe arabe"; an Arab restaurant
      LL Lichtenstern & Harari, Cairo; ND phot.; Cafes; Food; Restaurants
  - Subseries 4. Men and Occupations
    - Men and occupationsn.d., 24 postcards (Box 3, Folder 15)
      These postcards contain both "typical" images of men and images depicting various occupations. Most are from North Africa and Egypt. Images include: African warrior; an Arab sheik; rural Arabs; water porters from the M'zab and elsewhere; Sais; Arab merchants; lemonade sellers; donkey boys; olive oil mill; farmer; snake keepers; camel keepers; goat herders.
      A.C. Broggini, Milan and Cairo; Anciens Etab. Neurdein et Cie., Paris; CAP Collection Ideale P.S.; E. D'amico, editeur, Tunis; Lehnert & Landrock, Cairo; Levy Fils & Cie., Paris; Lichtenstern & Harari, Cairo; R. Prouho; Camels; Donkeys; Farmers; Goats; Indigenous peoples; Lemonade sellers; Men; Merchants; Snakes; Water carriers
  - Subseries 5. Missionaries
    - Missionariesn.d., 14 postcards (Box 3, Folder 16)
      These postcards were all published by missionary orders. Some depict the missionary work itself, while others show the terrain. From L'Oeuvre de la Propagation de la Foi: in the Canadian north; 2 young Eskimos; Hospital of the Soeurs de St-Joseph de l'Apparition in Mateur, Tunisia; Soeurs Bleues de Castres, Libreville, Congo; young Christian couples, Congo; meeting of 2 missionaries, Madagascar; class in orphanage, Asia; catechism, Oceania. Other images include: "virgin forest"; Mhonda waterfalls; coconut trees; travelling nuns; travelling missionaries; church in the wilderness.
      Congregation des Filles de la Croix de Liege; Fides Photo.; Helio Braun, Paris; L'Oeuvre de la Propagation de la Foi, Paris; Missions des P.P. du Saint-Esprit; Phototype J. Bienaime, Reims; Societeit voor Afrikaansche Missien; Indigenous peoples; Missionaries; Religious
  - Subseries 6. Religion
    - Religionn.d., 22 postcards (Box 3, Folder 17)
      These postcards depict religious rituals, primarily in North Africa. Images include the following: crowds praying in the desert; evening prayers; solitary prayer in the desert; reading of the Koran; mosques; marabout (religious person) in the oasis; funeral rites.
      CAP; Collection Ideale, P.S.; J. Geiser, Algiers; Imp. Adolphe Trinchant, Toulouse; LL ND Phot.; Camels; Desert; Funeral rites and ceremonies; Indigenous peoples; Mosques; Prayer
  - Subseries 7. Women
    - Womenn.d., 34 postcards (Box 3, Folder 18)
      These postcards depict women, individual or in groups, apparently with the intent of showing the exoticness of Arab and African women. Many images of veiled women, or of women in stages of undress. Also images of urban indigenous women in European dress. Several photos also depict women working - washing, grinding grain; dancing; cooking; and farming.
      CAP Collection Ideale, P.S., Algiers; Collection Z.F., Algiers; Congregation des Filles de la Croix de Liege; Edition "Au Chinois", Algiers; Edition Fr. Vester & Co., Jerusalem; Editions Photo-Africaines, Algiers; F. & L. Costa, Tunis; Isaac Behar, Port-Said; J. Geiser, Algiers; LL Lehnert & Landrock, Cairo; Les Redemptoristes en A.O.F., Paris; ND Phot. Neurdein et Cie., Paris; Arab women; Women; Families
  - Subseries 8. Europe
    - Europen.d., 6 postcards (Box 3, Folder 19)
      These 6 postcards show scenes of Europe (Belgium, England, France, Germany, Spain). Two especially are of interest: One showing a procession of Arab or South Asian men parading on horseback down a street that apppears to be in Europe (Paris?); one of a Somali mother and child on exhibit in a park in Germany.
      Edition L. Duparque, Florenville (Belgium); Lycee de St-Rambert; S. Koefman Tobacconist, Salisbury, England; V.B. Cumbo; Colonial power; Hotels; Parades and processions; Schools; Street scenes
  - Subseries 9. Ottoman Empire and Middle East
    - Ottoman Empire, Balkans, and Middle Eastn.d., 7 postcards (Box 3, Folder 20)
      These postcards are from several places in the Balkans, Ottoman Empire, and the Middle East. Ottoman Empire: Istanbul: panoramic views, Hagia Sofia Bosnia: Mostar, Syria: Aleppo: monastery of the praying dervishes, Afghanistan: caravan on its way to Peshawar, Pakistan, Crew of Arab ship (location unknown)
      K.G. Mehra & Sons, Peshawar; Meisenbach Riffarth & Co, Leipzig; Thacker & Co., Ltd.; Boats; Caravans; Mosques; Religious buildings; Street scenes
  - Subseries 10. Miscellaneous Geography and Subjects
    - Miscellaneous geography and subjects, unidentified locationsn.d., 14 postcards (Box 3, Folder 21)
      These postcards are from a variety of inadequately identified locations. Some locations, while noted, do not fit into present geographical categories. The subjects are as follows: Map of French West Africa; fishing boats on river; harbor; colonial street scenes; Zambesi: piano and seance; cotton cultivation; street with donkeys
      Imprimerie M. Lescuyer, Lyon; McCorquodale & Co., London; Phototypie J. Bienaime, Reims; Societe des Missions Evangeliques, Paris; Agriculture; Architecture, colonial; Harbors; Indigenous peoples; Maps; Rivers; Street scenes